Things are getting weird for little
human brain friends. You know, the tiny
human brains that you can grow from stem
cells and have run a computer. For the
last several years, since the inception
of these little guys, researchers have
been trying to incorporate them with AI
and figure out how to make them better.
Yes, tiny human brains make pretty
decent computation tools, and there's a
cloud that you can utilize them
remotely. Two companies now, Final Spark
and Cortical Labs, have opened up
operations where they deploy thousands
of these little guys in a warehouse and
sell their computation remotely online.
And of course, we have the very first
brain organoid computer that you can
purchase. It cost about $30,000
and you have to grow the brain organoids
yourself. They live for about 6 months,
although some researchers have gotten
them to live for a year or more. And
they work better in groups. We've also
seen them operate a variety of different
kinds of robots. They're very good with
spatial recognition. They can move
around a room and operate a body, which
makes sense because our brains were kind
of evolved to operate a body. My
favorite is the spider robot. This was
conceived by Allison Motri in UC San
Diego. I'm still waiting on the paper
from this. He told me it would come out
in 2024, but I've yet to see the paper
published. We've also seen them operate
snake robots. This one came from a group
that wanted to see if they could
replicate the two halves of the brain
and put two brain organoids in charge of
running a snake robot. It worked. My
hypothesis is people are trying to
figure out the creepiest possible body
to put these guys in. But back to this
paper, there are some limitations on the
brain organoids. It's hard to keep them
alive for a long period of time. They
almost always expire from hypoxia. That
is a problem because the longer they're
alive, the more complex they grow to be
and the better they are at computation.
I would have thought that you would want
a single type of neuron to perform these
tasks, but no, they do better in groups
and they do better with complex neural
structures. So, why not just grow them
in a tower? That's exactly what they
did. They grew them from single cells in
matriel, which is essentially mouse
tumor jell-o. This gel allows them to
grow into each other. They'll grow into
just about anything next to each other.
They operate very much like Legos. You
can just pop them together. In this
case, they were just grown near each
other and they grew little projections
into other organoids. It actually does
work. And the more that are together,
the more complex their brain waves
become. You can see day 30 here with
just 30 in the chip. But with 22 all in
tandem, you can see they have much more
complex brain waves. Each one of these
is an individual. And yeah, you can
imagine if one perishes, when they add
another, it can retrain it. This could
allow them to do specific tasks, which
we've already seen them get better at
when operating in a chip just with 16.
There really is no limit here. You could
have thousands of brain organoids all
working together. We haven't really seen
what kind of complex behaviors emerge
when you have quite that many. You could
also have individual brain components,
each operating a different lobe of the
brain coming together, and it might give
us interesting computation power. I say
interesting. We really don't know the
capabilities of these guys. Now, when
these guys were grown on a computer chip
like Final Spark does, they have 16
organoids to a chip. So, if one expires,
another one can just come in and the
others can train it. But if they're
communicating through actual physical
neural pathways rather than a computer
chip through electrodes, it does go
faster. I could see an array like this
work. If one of them expires, which does
tend to happen, they could excise it out
and pop a new one in. and they do pretty
well growing into other neural
structures. We've seen examples where
you took a brain organoid, grew it near
the decapitated spine of a mouse, and it
made projections and can even take
control of the muscles of the mouse that
is no longer a mouse. They have no
problem hybridizing with anything. You
can make mouse human brain organoids.
You can pop a brain organoid into the
skull of a live mouse and it'll make
connections and start working with the
mouse brain. They are essentially fetal
brains. And if there's one thing we know
about human brains is they'll just grow
with anything. Do the best with what you
got. That's why people who are born
without limbs tend to use their other
limbs pretty well. We adapt. What the
brain structure will allow us to do is
more complex computation. Brain
organoids aren't good at handling data
from LLMs, for example. They're not very
good with linear information. They can
learn language, though. They're far
better when utilized for things like
controlling a body or finding their way
through spatial information. So,
navigation, for example. Largely, what
brain organoids have been useful for is
medication testing and development. This
kind of structure could allow you to get
a lot of information from just one
little cube, or it could be used for
computation. This technology is still
pretty nent, for lack of a better pun.
This kind of structure could actually
allow us to have a brain organoid as
large as our own brains, just made out
of modular components suspended in mouse